Guide to the Bellingham Woman's Music Club records 1917-2009
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Bellingham Woman's Music Club records
1917-2009
XOE_CPNWS0051bwmusic
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA, 98225-9123 360 650 7747 cpnws@wwu.edu
9.25 linear feet.
The records of the Bellingham Woman’s Music Club, spanning 1917-2009, document its members’ contribution to Bellingham’s cultural development. The collection includes administrative records, financial records, yearbooks, activities records, scrapbooks, and reference materials.
Bellingham Woman's Music Club
Biographical/Historical note
The Bellingham Woman’s Music Club was organized February 22, 1916. It provided a forum for its members to perform musical selections and it organized performances by its members and professionals from elsewhere for the benefit of the public. The club was composed of both active members, who performed, and associate members, who were permitted to attend the meetings. By 1924 it was federated with the Washington State Federation of Music Clubs and the National Federation of Music Clubs. The club endeavored to involve itself in the community. Some of these efforts included providing concerts, offering scholarships for membership, and a large donation of record albums to the public library with station KVOS and Western Washington College of Education.
The records of the Bellingham Woman’s Music Club, spanning 1917-2009, document its members’ contribution to Bellingham’s cultural development. The collection includes administrative records, financial records, yearbooks, activities records, scrapbooks, and reference materials.
The Administrative Records, spanning from 1916-2006, include minutes, the club constitution, membership information and presidential records. Minutes contain summaries of meetings, musical selections performed by the active members at the meetings, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and printed programs of the performances and activities the club sponsored. The minute books begin in 1917 and end in 2006. The Presidential Records, 1978-2009, contains binders of records collected and maintained by past presidents and treasurers. Include copies of minutes, budget information, club by-law changes, lists of members, program information, etc.
Financial Records, 1940-2004, contains a treasurer's book as well as materials regarding financial and budget information. The yearbooks, 1917-2008, record the officers of the club and include the events planned for the year. Some of the yearbooks are missing, but can be found pasted into either the minute books or the scrapbooks.
The activities records, 1918-2008, document some of the various activities of the Bellingham Woman's Music Club. This includes: programs of events, information regarding National Music week and the Helen Snelling Memorial Award granted by the club.
The scrapbooks. 1941-1988, include printed programs of musical performances and social activities, photographs, newspaper clippings, and correspondence.
Reference Materials, spanning 1948-2007, include various materials collected by the club including newspaper articles about musicians and club member, manuals and handbooks, and mayoral decrees regarding the club.
The Bellingham Woman's Music Club records are organized in accordance with the following series and subseries arrangement:
Series I: Administrative Records, 1917-1968
Sub-series 1. Minute Books, 1917-1968
Sub-series 2. Club Constitutions, 1923-1950
Sub-series 3. Member Sponsorship Cards, 1960-1961
Sub-series 4. Presidential Records, 1978-2009
Series II: Financial Records, 1940-2004
Series III: Yearbooks, 1917-2008
Series IV: Activities Records, 1918-2008
Series V: Scrapbooks, 1941-1988
Series VI: Reference Materials, 1948-2007
The collection is open to the public.
Bellingham Woman's Music Club - Archives.
Music--Washington (State)--Bellingham--Societies, etc.--History--Sources.; Scrapbooks--Washington (State).; Women--Washington (State)--Bellingham--Societies and clubs--History--Sources.
Arts and Humanities; Performing Arts; Women
- Administrative Records, 1916-1968; Series I
  - Minutes, 1916-1968
    - Minute Book, 1916-1919 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Minute Book, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Minute Book, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Minute Book, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Minute Book, 1925-1927 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Minute Book, 1928-1935 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Minute Book, 1935-1942 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Minute Book, 1942-1949 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Minute Book, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Minute Book, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Minute Book, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Minute Book, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Minute Book, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Minutes, 1985-2006 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Club Constitutions, 1916-1950
    - Constitutions, 1916-1950 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Member Information, 1960-1961
    Additional cards may be found in later volumes of the minute books.
    - Membership sponsorship cards, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Membership Lists, 1988, 1993, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Presidential Records, 1978-2009
    - President's Binder, 1978-1992 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - President's Binder, May 1992-1997 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - President's Binder, August 1997-1998 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - President's Binder, September 1998- December 1999 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - President's Binder, January 2000-2004 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - President's Binder, September 2004 -December 2007 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - President's Binder, August 2008-2009 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - President's Correspondence, 1979-1986 (Box-folder 2/14)
- Financial Records, 1940-2004
  - Treasurer's Book, 1940-1966 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Financial Statements and Budget Information, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Bank Account Ledger, 1950-1992 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Tax Form and Piano Appraisal, 2004 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Yearbooks, 1917-1972; Series II
  - Yearbooks, 1917-1920 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Yearbooks, 1920-1930 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Yearbooks, 1930-1940 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Yearbooks, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Yearbooks, 1950-1961 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Yearbooks, 1961-1970 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Yearbooks, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Yearbooks, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Yearbooks, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Yearbooks, 2000-2008 (Box-folder 3/14)
- Activities, 1918-2008
  - General, 1990s (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Programs, 1918-2008 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - National Music Week, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Helen Snelling Memorial Award, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 3/18)
- Scrapbooks, 1941-1988; Series III
  - Scrapbooks, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Scrapbooks, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1952-1964 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Scrapbooks, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Scrapbooks, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1963-1974 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Scrapbooks, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1978-1988 (Box-folder 9/5)
- Reference Materials, 1948-2007
  - Manual of the National Federation of Music Clubs, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Handbooks, 1960-1979 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Music Clubs Magazine, 1987 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1948-2007 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Mayoral Proclamations, 1981-2004 (Box-folder 10/5)